If you haven't watched the first
video on query tuning, highly
recommend it, where we start with
heaps and then move into clustered
indexes, which are created when
you establish a primary key.
And now we'll look at query tuning
through the lens of non-clustered
indexes. And these are the
indexes that you can use to
help make code more efficient.
And a non-clustered index is
a separate data structure.
It's also a B-tree. So if you first
think about the clustered index,
that's how it's physically stored
in pages in your database files.
And you can only have one
clustered index because
you can only physically
store something one way.
So you think about your closet. You
can organize your closet one way,
and you can't really do anything
else to that closet, but you
could create a little sheet
of paper on the door that kind
of creates a map to certain
areas of your closet. So it's not
physical storage, but it's kind
of a logical way to organize.
And so a non-clustered index
is not physical. It's in the
form of a B-tree. It's not
physical, but it also provides a
roadmap, and that roadmap
includes links to your original or
pointers to your original
clustered index. And so the idea
of a non-clustered index is
to make things more efficient,
and in a sense you think of
the back of a textbook where
you have an index where you
can quickly look things up so
it's not the physical pages
like your first pages prior to
an index but it does help you
find things more efficiently
but it doesn't physically
change how anything is stored
and other than a pointer
is provided to help quickly
link to these row IDs using
row IDs in a clustered index.
This diagram is really good
illustration of a non-clustered
index because you first have
your database itself. So
again, think of your closet.
It's physically storing things.
And then the non-clustered index,
like that piece of paper you
stick on the door that kind of
points to things where they are
located to help make it easier
to find things in your closet.
and then the way the data are
outputted or found are based
on both the physical and the
logical non-clustered index.
Now, you can't just create a non
-clustered index on everything. That
would eventually slow things down,
and that might be something you have
a short conversation with AI on
regarding having too many non-clustered
indexes. But the idea of even
covering the topic of query tuning,
The textbook that Ben Gaughan uses
is almost, I think, like 850 pages.
So we're condensing and trying to
get at least one path through or
a slice through where you can
understand heaps, clustered index,
and now we're looking at the non
-clustered index, which is really
the things that give you power to
make your code more efficient. Now,
a non-clustered index, you typically
look at the where clause, a
join, and an order by in order to
make the queries more efficient.
And we'll look at a couple of these,
and then your lab will take you
into a little bit more detail.
So let's take a look at the first
one. And I may have shown this in
your introductory class just as a
harbinger to query tuning. but the
number one rule that we'll start
with on query tuning is if you if
you don't need the order by then
don't use it and if you are always
or frequently needing an order by
that's when you can create a non
-clustered index and again the non
-clustered index typically occurs to
make a where a join and an order by
more efficient and then in a
minute I'll explain how a select
statement, you'll use the word include
to add some columns in your select
statement that are necessary so
you don't do what's called a key
lookup, but we'll get to that in just
a minute. So speaking of the this
or that, these are the two options
we have. We can select the top
5,000 rows and then sale ID,
sale date, customer ID from
the sale table and order
by sale date, Or the other
option is we don't use the
order by. So let me copy this
code into SQL Server, and
then we'll take a look at it.
Let's take a look at our top
5,000 rows from the DBO sale.
And these DDL, DML will
be provided in the module.
Or if it's not, the data files aren't in
the module. They're
certainly under files.
but I'll try to provide a
link to that or at least
an announcement to point
you to the files to run
this code for both the
video activity and the lab.
So we run this code. I do have
this option, recompile. The idea,
and I don't know if it's the
best code to use, but the idea
would be to clear out the cache
after this runs so it's a little
bit easier to keep track of how
efficiently things are running so
it's not just stored in cache,
which would tend to run faster.
But if If we run this code, we get
our output, and then our executed
execution plan is here. Our
actual execution plan is here.
The database engine is so efficient,
though, we should be able to
use the estimated execution plan
for most of our query tuning.
So I'm going to click on this
estimated plan, and on the plan, again,
we'll read it from right to left.
If we put our mouse cursor over the
cluster, you can see in this case
it's doing a clustered index scan.
So it's finding information from
each row or from each page in our
clustered index because it's
grabbing every data point we have.
The cost of it, it looks like 41.
We have 41 rows that are going
to be read and then it tells how
fast it is and then the IO cost is
just how many times it's connecting
or reconnecting to our input
and output. code. And so when we
read it, 100% of the cost is this
scan, we use the top function,
which doesn't cost anything. So 100
% of the cost is our clustered index
scan. And if I go to the other
option, which is the order by, so
now we have order by sale date.
And order by sale date
is not the clustered
index, I think the
clustered index is sale ID.
So And so if we run this code,
you can see 20% of the cost
is that clustered index scan.
On the other one, it was 100.
And then 78% of the cost
of this is this order buy.
If this 22%, if the original scan that we
did, 100% of it, let's
say it took 10 seconds.
Now, almost 80% of it is
this sort and cost. So we
would have to add, what,
another 40 seconds to this?
80%. So this would cost
about 50 seconds compared to
10 seconds. So depending on
the data size, it can be a
very significant cost by
using the order by. And now
we'll take a look at how we
can potentially fix that.
So these are the two comparables.
The top one here, reading from right
to left 22% of the cost is to scan
here 20 100% is to scan 78% so more
than you know more than far more of
the cost is built in that order by
and so now let's take a look at how
we can solve that and clearly one
of them the item that we're going to
create is a non-clustered index on
and in this case I think it was
sale date so so we know that's the
initial goal and then we'll find in a
minute that we also need to use include
to add some columns from the select
statement stick with me here some
columns from the select statement
so that it will also run efficiently
because if we don't have those
included then that non-clustered index
just on the order by doesn't necessarily
help us you can see here that
that top and sort which took up
78 of the cost is very inefficient
because first you have to filter it
and then you have to sort it and then
you can finally look into the rows.
But it creates something of a loop
where each row has to be independently
looked at in order to figure out
how to sort. Think about ordering
blocks or something. It takes a long
time in order to figure out A to
Z, put things in order. And it's an
expensive cost, in this case, 78%.
Where when we just did the top function,
everything was already ordered. It
just grabbed from the data file,
grabbed the top. In fact, it probably
made it a little more efficient
because it didn't have to grab
all of the data in the data set.
And so that doesn't slow
the data set down. But
let's take a look at
our non-clustered index
and see how we're going to use
it. Now, what we're thinking
of is we want to create a non
-clustered index on sale date.
And this isn't typed quite right.
Let me go to the next one here.
So this is what we're thinking to
type. So create a non-clustered index,
IX, I keep moving my mouse,
sorry, IX for non-clustered
index, sales, the name of the
table, sale date, and then we use
the on clause like we use in
a join, on, we need the full
schema, so dbodatabaseowner
.sale, and then sale date is
going to be our non-clustered
index. So let me run this code.
We have it successful.
Then let's go back to the
one with the order by.
So we do have a non
-clustered index on sale date.
Very cool.
So let me execute that.
Or we could have just
hit the execution plan.
But it looks good,
right? 25% of the cost.
But remember, 78% of the cost
was that order by. Now we have
this thing called key lookup,
which is taking 73%. So we're
not much better. And then we
have a nested loop with the top.
And then that's our cost. And
also on the left, it does give
you more information on the entire
cash plan and execution plan.
And then before I forget,
too, under each table, as you
expand your tables, so this
one was done on the sale table.
But as you expand your tables,
you can find indexes. And
then if I refresh, we certainly
have clustered indexes.
What did we create? This
one on the sale table.
So if I scroll down to the sale table,
and right now it just has the
clustered index, but we created,
didn't we create another one? So
there you can see the clustered
index that we created. So we
can right-click and drop it.
But we have this key
lookup. And let's take
a look at what that
key lookup problem is.
All right. So we ran
this non-clustered index.
It made things just a
little bit more efficient.
It created the non
-clustered index on sale
date, so this would run more efficiently.
The problem is, in our select
statement, we have sale ID.
Now, sale ID is our clustered
index, so it's okay.
But the challenge we have is
when it's running this code
and order buying, this is
ordered now through that B tree,
through a non-clustered index,
but there's an additional
line of code that we
need to add to our non
-clustered index to make this
work the way it's written.
And what we do is we include,
we used the word include,
and we indicate the columns
that are not in a clustered index. So
if you see sale date and customer ID,
that is currently causing the
problem with this key lookup. And so
every time it's running, we have
the non-clustered index on sale
date. That's fine. But each time
it's doing that, it has to go and
look up those two columns. columns,
the two additional columns.
And so that is what's creating our
problem. And we don't want to see
key lookup just like we don't
want to see top in order because
effectively it has to do a complete
loop on every row in the data set.
And so this is extremely
expensive. The nice thing is
SQL server, as you can see
under tune tips, says add
missing columns as include
that will cover this query.
If you look, I'm going to drop the index.
I'm doing it this way. I could also
right-click over here, but this is fancy.
Now we've dropped that. What
we want to do is we still
want to do the same thing.
Our index is going to be
on sale, but you can see
the additional code there to
address the columns. Include
sale ID and customer ID.
Sale date is already included
there, and I don't think
we'd have to include sale
ID, but let's leave it
in for now because it's
already on a clustered index.
But I'm going to paste this
code in, create a non-clustered
index. Everything is the same,
and it's on the sale date.
We want to include these
columns, which are not part of
the clustered index. We only
have sale date as part of it.
So effectively, we're creating a
non-clustered index with these added
effectively to our pointer, we're
adding this include to our pointer
to make it more efficient so it
doesn't have to go back to the main
table storage in order to efficiently
run. So now we've run this code
to create the index. And
then if we run this code
here, we execute it. Oh,
it seemed a little faster.
Not enough rows probably seem
faster. But now if we do the check,
if you look at this, is it's
the same as if we didn't use the
order by we have 100% of the cost
is the non clustered index scan.
And this this runs effectively
like we didn't have the order by
at all. So what we had to do
two things include the sale date
as our main non clustered index.
And then because we had sale
ID and customer ID, in addition
to the sale date, we would
include those there. And again,
I don't think you would need sale
ID because that's a clustered
index. So that's I don't you would
be find without that. So you
could have run it without this.
And now we have it running perfectly
or as efficient as possible. And
we get rid of that problematic key
lookup, which is another super slow.
So the non-clustered index is a
lot of times it's going to have two
parts to it. The non-clustered index,
for instance, the order by sale
date. And then the second part
are just which columns do you want
to run that, which columns do you
want to run. And if they're not in
the include statement, then it's
just as if you didn't create the non
-clustered index because it would
still have to go to the physical
and loop around each time. So that's
quite a firehose of information.
But by using include, you're going
from this problem, the original one,
without a non-clustered index to
a regular non-clustered index with
just the sale date, which gives us
this darn key lookup. And then by
adding the word include, we go and we
do a nice index scan and this looks
perfect. And then we can drop that.
We can drop that non
-clustered index and look at
another problem. And
I'll wrap this up for now
as our video two covering
the order by clause.
We'll be right back.